<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: DIY | Exhortatory]]></title>
  <link href="http://jdodds.github.com/blog/categories/diy/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jdodds.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-10-08T18:00:20-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://jdodds.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jeremiah Dodds]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[jeremiah.dodds@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DIY Everything]]></title>
    <link href="http://jdodds.github.com/blog/2012/09/16/diy-everything/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-16T12:13:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jdodds.github.com/blog/2012/09/16/diy-everything</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Every once in a while I hear people talking about how they'd like to have some
useful product, but can't afford it. Sometimes they complain about how they
can't afford it. Sometimes, very rarely, this is legitimate.</p>

<p>We live in a time where the knowledge necessary to do almost anything is at our
fingertips. Can't afford new shelves? They're easy to rig up -- even some rope,
eyelet screws, and wood will do the trick if it needs to.</p>

<p>Can't afford a projector? If you can get your hands on a transparency projector
from a school that's getting rid of them, or from
<a href="http://www.freecycle.org/">freecycle</a> or
<a href="http://www.craigslist.org">craigslist</a> or similar, you can get a LED screen
with a busted backlight off of <a href="http://www.ebay.com">ebay</a> for very cheap and
have yourself a functioning projector in little time.</p>

<p>People seem to make the assumption that they <strong>aren't capable</strong> of doing things
themselves, and the reasons that people do that are myriad. I'm of the opinion
that a lot of it stems from people being surrounded from birth by a culture that
promotes consumerism as solution, but that's a can of worms that would be a
better fit for another post.</p>

<p>Making your own stuff is incredibly rewarding. We're a species that depends on
pattern-matching for survival, doing things makes us better at doing
things. Anytime you try to acquire a new skill, there will be a period of
frustration at the beginning before things "click". It's often touted that ten
thousand hours of practice at something will make someone a master at that, and
the few actual attempts at that have had great results. It takes much, much less
time to gain a basic level of competence.</p>

<p>As an example, I taught myself to juggle a few years ago. It took three days of
practice for me to be able to do the most basic three-ball cascade. Once I got
that down, it became much easier to start learning more complex tricks, and
although I haven't been practicing regularly for a while now, I can still throw
a three-ball cascade with ease.</p>

<p>The point of all this is that if you wish you had something, sit down, figure
out a way that could potentially provide that something, and then create
it. Rinse, repeat.</p>

<p>It's the most empowering thing I know of, and it's never been easier to be
empowered. We can do amazing things, humanity. We've done amazing things. Let's
do more.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
