<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: crowdfunding | Exhortatory]]></title>
  <link href="http://jdodds.github.com/blog/categories/crowdfunding/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jdodds.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-08-24T19:10:51-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://jdodds.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jeremiah Dodds]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[jeremiah.dodds@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kickstarter's Appeal Process]]></title>
    <link href="http://jdodds.github.com/blog/2012/08/23/kickstarters-appeal-process/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-23T04:47:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://jdodds.github.com/blog/2012/08/23/kickstarters-appeal-process</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the reasons that I decided to attempt to maintain
<a href="https://github.com/jdodds/aif">aif</a> was because it's very relevant to something
I've wanted to do for a long time -- make it easy to create customized Linux
live and install images that have the setup you want available in the live
environment and immediately after a fresh install.</p>

<p>While I'm capable of accomplishing that from a technical standpoint, I can't
currently afford much of anything, let alone the hosting costs associated with
creating and serving install images -- it's intensive in terms of CPU use,
memory, and network usage.</p>

<p>I decided to try to start a <a href="http://www.kickstarter.com/">kickstarter</a> for
funding the project. I spent a good amount of time reviewing their project
guidelines, and figuring out how to take a decent video of both myself talking,
and of a proof-of-concept app doing it's thing. When I went to submit it for
review, I had sent out a preview link to quite a few people, and gotten nothing
but positive feedback.</p>

<p>To my surprise, my submission was declined, and the reason given was what looked
like a simple form letter saying that I wasn't within their project
guidelines. Kickstarter allows you to appeal for re-approval, which I did, but
they only allow you 500 <em>characters</em> with which to do so, a bit on the short end
if you don't provide any feedback as to why a submission is declined.</p>

<p>After submitting the appeal, I received the same form letter back. Exactly the
same.</p>

<p>It's a bit aggravating -- I can see how my project would have not been
considered the type of thing that kickstarter is for, but if I was being denied
on a whim, I would have preferred that to be stated explicitly. As it is, it's
not hard at all to browse through successfully funded projects that are either
in blatant violation of one of their "project guidelines", or that are at least
as interpretable as such as mine was.</p>

<p>Back in 2011, <a href="http://www.kalzumeus.com/">Patrick McKenzie</a> gave a talk at
Google called
<a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sFWlmEO6eg0&amp;list=UUtXKDgv1AVoG88PLl8nGXmw">What Engineers Don't Know We Don't Know About Online Marketing</a>,
where he brought up how incredibly bad the support from Google was when
someone's AdWords account would be suspended, and how it was really, <em>really</em> in
their best interests to do something about that. I hope Kickstarter starts
providing more (or any) feedback to people they deny submissions from at some
point, but I suppose we'll just have to wait and see.</p>

<p>In any case, I've since taken what would have been my kickstarter campaign, and
started it at <a href="http://www.indiegogo.com/customized-linux">indiegogo</a>. Take a
look at it if you're so inclined, or show it to your neckbeard friends. I'd
really like to bring the idea to fruition.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
